欢迎回来, 在这个视频中, 我将展示如何使用正则表达式
Welcome back. In this video, I'm going to show how to use regular expressions to
指定编程语言的不同方面, 必须从关键字开始
specify different aspects of programming languages. Must begin with the keywords
这是一个相对简单的例子, 我将用三个关键字来做。
and this serves a relatively simple case and I'll just do it for three keywords.
我将写一个正则表达式如果, else, 或者那么它就会很明显
I'll write a regular expression for if, else, or then and it would be obvious how
为了更多, 我们来写一个正则表达式如果这样的话
to do it for more. So let's write a regular expression for if and that would
对i进行正则表达式, 然后是f的正则表达式
be under regular expression for i. And followed by the regular expression for f
我们把这两个连接起来, 然后我们要结合
and we're taking the concatenation of these two. And then we're going to union
这是用正则表达式来表示的, 这是什么呢？
that with the regular expression for else and what is that? Well, else consist of
四个单独的字符所以我们必须写出这四个字符的串联
four individual characters so we have to write out a concatenation of those four
你可以看到, 这些都有点啰嗦
characters. And, as you can see this is a little bit verbose with all of these
引用和读起来有点乱, 事实上, 这是一个很短的手
quotes and kind of messy to read. So in fact, there's a short hand that's normally
用过, 现在让我切换到这个, 如果我想写规则
used and let me switch over to that right now. So if I want to write the regular
一个字符表达式序列的表达式, 我可以
expression for a sequence of single character expressions, I could just
听不清, 围绕着序列中最外层的字符, 举个例子
[inaudible] around the outermost characters in the sequence. So for example
大多数让你写这个的工具, 我在开始的时候引用了一个引语
most of the tools that let you write this, I put a quote at the beginning right IF
然后我关闭引号, 这意味着完全一样的东西, 这是
and then I close quote and this means exactly The same thing as this. This is
两个单字符正则表达式的连接, 类似的,
the concatenation of two single character regular expression and similarly for else,
类似的, 如果我有更多的关键字, 我就把它们写出来
And similarly for them. And if I have more keywords I'll just write them out and
现在, 让我们考虑一个稍微复杂一点的例子。
union them altogether. Now, let's consider a slightly more complicated example. Let's
考虑一下如何指定想要成为非空字符串的整数
think about how to specify the integers who want to be the non-empty strings of
数字, 这里的第一个问题是写出一个数字是什么, 这是
digits. So the first problem here is to write out what a digit is and that's
很简单, 一个数字就是任何一个单独的字符0
pretty straight forward. A digit is just any of the individual characters zero
通过9, 我们已经知道如何写出单个字符了
through nine and we already know how to write out single character regular
表达式, 它是10个这样的组合来指定这个, 它会带我
expressions. And it's just a union of ten of those to specify this and it'll take me
稍等一下, 我们开始, 这是一组正则表达式
just a moment to finish. Here we go. So that's a regular expression for the set of
字符串对应于所有的单个数字, 因为我们想要引用
strings correspondin g to all the single digits. And because we want to refer to
这是一种很常见的现象, 也是最常见的
this from time to time and also because as a very common thing to watch too, most
工具有一个用于命名正则表达式的工具, 例如, 我可以命名
tools have a facility for naming regular expressions. So for example I can name
这个是数字所以一个数字是任何产生的或者是在
this one to be digit so a single digital is anything that is generated or is in the
由这个正则表达式表示, 现在我们要做的是
set denoted by this regular expression. And now what we want to do is to have
多位数, 我们知道一种方法, 我们可以对一个数字进行迭代
multiple digits. Well, we know a way to do that. We can just iterate a single digit
就像我们喜欢的次数一样, 这里我们得到了所有的字符串, 所有可能的字符串
as many times as we like. And so here we get all strings, all possible strings of
数字和这个非常非常接近我们想要的除了这个字符串
digits and this is very, very close to what we wanted except that the string that
我们想要的是非空的, 我们不想把空字符串算作整数。
we want has to be non-empty. We don't want to count the empty string as an integer.
这是一种简单的方法, 我们只是说整个序列必须
And there's an easy way to do that. We just say that the whole sequence has to
从一个数字开始, 然后是零个或更多的数字
begin with a single digit and then it's followed by zero or more additional digits
所以, 只是重申一下, 我们看到至少有一个数字
so just. Is just to reiterate that, we see there has to be at least one digit and is
然后是零更多的数字, 这个模式实际上是为给定的
followed by zero more additional digits. And this pattern actually for a given
语言是非常普遍的, 所以如果我想说我至少有一个a
language is extremely common. So if I wanted to say that I have at least one a I
把它写成a, 因为它有零个或更多a, 第二部分是零
write that as a, a because this has zero or more a, the second part is zero more
a和第一部分说必须至少有一个a, 因为这是
a's and the first part says there has to be at least one a. And because this is so
很常见, 有一个很短的手, 我认为是每个规则的支持
common, there's a short hand for it. I think is supported by every regular
表达式处理器, 就是写一个加号, a+的意思是, 只是a
expression processor and that is to write a plus. An a + means is just, is just a
对于一个恒星来说是短的, 所以我们可以简化这个正则表达式
short hand for a star. And so we can actually simplify this regular expression
再写一个简单的数字加, 现在, 让我们看另一个例子
a bit and write simply digit plus. Now, let's look at yet another example even
比前两个更复杂, 让我们考虑一下如何定义
more sophisticated than the, the previous two. Let's think about how to define the
标识符是一串字母或数字以字母开头, 所以
identifiers which are strings of letters or digits that begin with a letter. And so
我们已经知道如何做数字了我们先把注意力集中在这些字母上吧
we already know how to do digits so let's focus on the letters for a moment. So how
我们会写出字母的正则表达式当我们要命名它的时候
we write out a regular expression for the letters while we're gonna name it. So
我们会说这些字母或者是一个字母, 现在我们要写一个字母
we'll say that the letters or actually a single letter. And now we have to write a
对所有单独的字母进行正则表达式这是, 你知道的
regula r expression for all the individual letters and that's, you know
很简单, 但很乏味, 我们必须说小写, 小写b, 小写c,
straightforward but tedious. We have to say little a, lower case b, lower case c,
小写d, 你可以看到, 这将会是一个很大的规则
lower case d. And well, as you can see, this is gonna be rather a large regular
我们将会有26个小写字母和26个大写字母
expression. We're going to have 26 lower case letters and 26 upper case letters and
整件事都是很乏味的写下来让我们来看看
the whole thing is going to be rather tedious as to write down so let's actually
不要那样做, 我要提一个简写, 一个工具支持来实现它
not do that. Instead, let me mention a shorthand, A tool support to make it
更容易写出这种正则表达式也就是所谓的
easier to write out exactly this kind of regular expression which is called the
字符范围, 在方括号内, 我可以写一个范围
character range. So inside your square brackets I can write a range of
字符, 那么我该怎么做呢, 我有一个起始字符和一个结尾
characters. So how do I do that? Well, I have the starting character and an ending
字符, 我用连字符隔开它们, 这意味着所有的结合
character and I separate them by a hyphen. And what this means is the union of all
单个字符, 正则表达式从第一个字符开始
the single character, regular expressions beginning with the first character and
以第二个字符结尾, 所以所有的东西都在中间, 所以这就是
ending with the second character, so everything in between. So this is exactly
所有小写字母的正则表达式然后我可以有另一个
the regular expression for all the lower case letters and then I can have another
字符范围, 在所有大写字母的相同的方括号中。
character range and so at the same square brackets for all the upper case letters.
所以A到Z, 对吧？右边的这个正则表达式定义了
So A through Z, Okay? And this regular expression here on the right defines
这就是我不想写的大联盟, 好吧, 这给了我们一个
exactly the big union that I didn't wanna write out, okay? And that gives us a
这是单个字母的定义现在我们的状态很好, 我们已经
definition of the single letter and now we're in great shape. We are, we already
对一个数字有定义, 我们已经有了字母的定义
have definition for a digit, we already now we have definition for letter and so
我们可以写出这个定义的其余部分, 所以我们想要整个规则
that we can write out the rest of this definition. So we want the whole Regular
表达式总是以字母开头的, 所以识别总是从a开始
expression to always begin with a letter. Okay, so identify always begins with a
字母和之后可以是一串字母或数字, 明白吗？
letter and after that is allowed to be a string of letters or digits, okay? So they
建议会有一个工会, 所以在第一封信之后, 我们可以
are suggest that there's going to be a union. So After the first letter we can
有一个字母或一个数字然后我们可以有任意的字符串
have either a letter or a digit and then we can have an arbitrary string of those
所以我们在整个事情上都有了一个开始这就是我们的定义
things. So we put a start on the whole thing and that is the definition of
标识符, 从一个字母开始然后是零个或多个字母
identifier. Begins with a single letter and it's followed by zero or more letters
还有数字, 因为我们在做一个完整的词汇规范, 我们也
and digits. So. Because we're doing a complete lexical specification, we also
还要处理我们不感兴趣的字符串的部分
have to deal with even the parts of the string that we're not really interested
我们至少要对它们进行说明这样我们才能识别和投掷
in. We have to have at least specification of them so then we can recognize and throw
它们消失了, 特别是我们必须能够识别出白色的空间。
them away. In particular we have to be able to recognize the white space and.
我们要把空白区域变成一个非空的空序列, 新行
We're just gonna take white space to be a non-empty sequence of blanks, new lines
还有标签, 尽管还有其他类型的空白字符, 比如
and tabs even though there are other kinds of white space characters. Things like
可能像rubout, 根据你的键盘, 可能还有其他的
maybe like rubout. Depending on your keyboard, there might be others but these
三个就足以说明所有的要点了, 所以, 你知道, 空白是
three will suffice to illustrate all the important points. So, you know, blank is
相对容易写下来, 这只是在空白区域的单引号
relatively easy to write down. That's just a single quote around the blank space but
在标签页中有一个新行的问题, 因为一个换行的新行
there's a problem with new line in tab. Because a new line that carries return in
这个文件有特殊的含义, 你知道, 在这条线上, 你结束了
the file has special meaning typically. You know, and on the line, you end
无论您在这个正则表达式工具中使用什么命令, 如SQL工具。
whatever command you're working on in this regular expression tools like SQL tools.
而且, 你知道, 标签也不是一件容易的事情, 它看起来不像
And, you know, tab also is not an easy thing to write down and it doesn't look
在很多情况下, 与空白有很大的不同, 所以, 它们提供了什么工具
much different from a blank in a lot of cases. So, what tools do is they provide
这是单独的名称, 通常是通过某种形式完成的
separate name for these and it's, and typically it's done by having some kind of
转义字符和反斜杠。是最常用的一个
escape character and a backslash. Is the most common one that's used and then
后面是字符的名字, 所以反斜杠n通常用于新的
followed by a name for the character? So back slash n is typically used for new
行和反斜杠t通常用于制表符, 我想强调的是
line and back slash t is typically used for tab. And I just want to stress I mean
做这个例子的原因是为了说明这一点, 我们必须有一个
the reason for doing this example is to illustrate this that. We have to have a
给一些字符命名的方法并没有很好的打印
way of naming some characters that don't really have a very nice print
代表, 还有其他的角色, 甚至没有任何类型的
representation. There are other characters that, that don't even have really any kind
我们仍然需要一种方法来在我们的日常生活中谈论它们
of print representation and we still need a way to talk about them in our regular
表达式, 因为它们可能被嵌入到一个文件中我们必须使用它
expressions because them might be embedded in a file that we have to lexically
在某一点上进行分析, 无论如何, 这样做的方式是提供a
analyze at some point. And so anyway, the way this is done is by providing a
单独的, 主要字符的命名方案, 通常是
separate. Naming scheme for such on principal characters and typically as the
一个是转义序列, 所以, 从像后面这样的特殊字符开始
one that escape sequence. So, something beginning with special character like back
然后是字符的名字, 所以, n代表新行和这个
slash followed by the name of the character. So, n for new line and this
选项卡, 为了结束我们的定义, 这给了我们, 你知道吗？1
case nt for tab. And so to finish off our definition, this gives us. You know? One
字符, 空格然后我们想要一个非空的序列或者这样的东西
character, white space and then we want a non empty sequence or such things so we
可以用括号把整个联合包裹起来, 然后加上一个加号。
could wrap the whole union there in parenthesis and put a plus on it and that.
给我们想要的东西, 让我们暂停一下讨论编程语言
Get us what we want. Let's pause for a moment in discussing programming languages
再看另一个使用不同的正则表达式的例子
and look at another example of using regular expressions from a different
域, 这里我有一个电子邮件地址, 结果是, 电子邮件地址形成a
domain. Here I have an e-mail address and as it turns out, e-mail addresses form a
世界上有规律的语言和电子邮件处理设备, 所以你
regular language and every e-mail processing device in the world. So your
邮件服务器和你使用的邮件服务器, 都进行正则表达式处理
mailer and the mail servers that you use, all do regular expression processing to
了解电子邮件地址在电子邮件中告诉他们的内容
understand what the e-mail address is telling them in the e-mail messages that
它们经过。所以我们可以想到一个电子邮件地址, 是由
they go by. And. And so we can think of an e-mail address is being, is consisting of
有四个不同的字符串用标点符号隔开, 有一个用户名, 然后
four different strings separated by punctuation. There's a username and then
这个域的三个部分, 好的, 让我们简单地假设
three parts to the domain. Okay. Let's just assume for simplicity that the
字符串只包含字母和练习它们可以由其他种类组成
strings only consist of letters and practice they can consist of other kinds
也有一些字符但是让我们把事情简单化, 我们可以把它写出来
of characters too but let's just keep things simple and we can write out the
使用正则表达式的更复杂的东西但是结构应该是
more complicated things using the regular expressions but the structure would be the
就像我们认为它们是由字母组成的一样, 然后这四个
same as if we just consider them to be made of letters. And then these four
字符串用标点符号隔开所以这里有@符号和小数点
strings are separated by punctuations so there's the @ sign and to decimal points
这是, 构成字符串的分隔符所以这是相对简单的
that's. Form the separators of the strings so these is a relatively straightforward
要写出一个正则表达式来给出我们目前所知道的用户名
thing to write a regular expression for given what we know so far so the user name
会是一个非空的字母序列然后是一个@
would be the non-empty sequence of letters and then that would be followed by an @
符号, 然后域的第一部分也会是空的
sign. And then the first part of the domain will also be on empty sequence of
字母后面跟着一个点然后剩下的都是一样的, 嘿, 我们在这里
letters followed by a dot and then the rest is just the same. Hey, so here we're
简单地说, 我们已经指定了大量的电子邮件地址, 就像我说的
quite concisely, we had specified large family of e-mail addresses. As I said in
现实, 电子邮件地址稍微复杂一些但可以写出来
reality the e-mail addresses are slightly more complicated but they can be written
用一个稍微复杂一点的正则表达式, 最后是最后一个
out with just a slightly more complicated regular expression. Finally for our last
例如, 让我们看一个真实的词汇规范的片段
example, let's look at a fragment of the lexical specification of a real
编程语言和这个案例语言是Pascal, 它在
programming language and this case that language is Pascal which is in the
听不清, 语言族, 帕斯卡是一种类型语言的早期例子
[inaudible] family of languages, Pascal is an early example of a type language and
它和Fortran和c在同一个大家庭中在这个特殊的片段中
it's in the same general family as Fortran and C. And in this particular fragment of
帕斯卡处理的是数字的定义, 让我们看一看。
pascal deals with the definition of numbers and so let's take a look here.
我从下面开始, 看看这个数字的总体定义是什么
I'll start at the bottom and look at what the overall definition of a number is. So
一个数字包含三个东西, 一些数字, 我把它读出来
a number consist of three things, some digits, and I'll just read out this
缩写和可选分数, 还有一个可选的指数我们在这里讨论
abbreviation and optional fraction. And an optional exponent so we're dealing here
有浮点数, 浮点数有很多
with floating point numbers and so a floating point number have a bunch of
数字, 然后它可以被跟踪可能是一个分数, 或者不是
digits and then it can be followed possibly by a fraction or not and that
可能会被一个指数, 或者不, 还有这个想法, 尽管我们
could be followed possibly by an exponent or not and. And the idea, although we
不能仅仅因为这个特定的定义就能看到它的作用或者是
can't see it just for this particular definition is that either of action or the
指数可以独立于另一个, 现在让我们简单地从
exponent can be present independent of the other. So, now let's work briefly from the
下面, 我们来检查一下我们期望的数字, 一个数字在里面
bottom up, let's just check the digits on what we expect. So a single digit is in
事实是所有的普通数字的结合正如我们所希望的那样, 然后
fact the union of all the common digits just as we would hope. And then a
非空的数字序列是一个数字加上这是我们已经看到的。
non-empty sequence of digit is a digit plus so this is what we've already seen.
现在有趣的是看看可选分数和可选部分
And now the interesting bid is to look at how the optional fraction and the optional
指数是定义的而可选分数看起来不那么吓人
exponent are defined and the optional fraction looks a little less scary so
我们先来做这个, 那么这个分数里面发生了什么呢, 如果我们有一个
let's do that one first. So what's going on inside the fraction, well if we have a
小数部分, 会有一个小数点, 后面跟着
decimal fraction, there is gonna be a decimal point and that's gonna be followed
用强的数字来表示这就是浮点数的小数部分
by strong of digits so this is just. The fractional parts of the floating point
它的值是在小数点之后, 这是什么呢
number it's just of it comes after the decimal point. And what's this plus
在这里做什么？记住, 加号是union, epsilon代表
epsilon doing out here? Well remember, the plus is union and epsilon stands for the
空字符串, 这就是说, 要么是
empty string. So what this is saying is that either the fractional portion of the
数字是存在的, 或者是完全不存在的, 这就是你怎么说的
number is present or it's completely absent. So this is how you say something
是可选的, 你写出了这个东西的正则表达式然后你就可以了
is optional. You write out the regular expression for the thing and then you do
在最后加上epsilon这意味着, 我之前说过的所有东西
plus epsilon at the end and that means well, either everything I said before it
可以在那里, 或者什么都没有, 对吧？可选的指数是结构化的
can be there or nothing is there. Okay? And the optional exponent is structured
类似地, 但有点复杂, 你可以看到整个指数是可选的
similarly but somewhat more complex. So, you can see the whole exponent is optional
因为这里有一些正则表达式, 这是与epsilon的结合, 所以
because there's some regular expression here. That's union with epsilon, And so
任何东西都在这里这是可选的, 或者这个指数部分或者不是
either Something is there and this is the optional, or this exponent part or is not
现在我们来看看指数是如何定义的。
present at all. And now let's look inside how the exponents define if it's there.
所以, 指数总是以e开头的, 所以这是指数, 你知道, 标准
So, an exponent always begins with e. So this is exponent, you know, standard
指数符号, 它总是有一个非空的数字串, 所以这是e
exponent notation and it always has a non-empty string of digits. So there's e
后面是一些数字, 中间有一个可选的符号, 我们知道符号
followed by some digits and in between, there's an optional sign. We know the sign
是可选的因为epsilon是一种可能性, 整个, 整个符号
is optional because epsilon is one of the possibilities. The whole, the whole sign
可能是不存在的, 这个符号的一个可能性是, 它可以
might be absent. And one of the possibilities for the sign, well, it could
是负的, 也可以是正的, 所以, 要么是正的, 要么是负的
be negative or it could be positive. So, either there's a positive or negative sign
或者没有符号, 在这种情况下, 它被解释为正的, 现在这个
or no sign. In which case, presumably, it's interpreted to be positive. Now this
我们有+epsilon的习语表明有些东西是可选的
idiom where we have + epsilon indicate that something is optional is also
这是非常普遍的所以很多工具都提供了另一个很短的手
extremely common and so there's another short hand that many tools provide so
另一种写法是, 这是我的分数
another way of writing this, that's common is to say that. That's my fractional
然后它可能就不存在了, 所以这个问题在一个规则之后
component and then it might be absent. So the question mark after a regular
表达式就是这个结构, 我们取它的规则
expression just means exactly this construction, that we take that regular
表达式, 我们或者和epsilon, 所以这个, 这个正则表达式是a, 是
expression and we or with epsilon. And so this one, this regular expression is a, is
稍微复杂一点, 有两个可选的组件我们来写一下
a little more complicated. There's two optional components so let's just write
这样我们就会得到指数从e开始, 然后
out what that would look like so we would have the exponent begins with e and then
我们有一个符号, 它是+或者-这是可选的所以我们输入一个问号
we have a sign. Which is either + or - and that's optional so we put a question mark
之后是一个非空的字符串或数字然后这整个就是
after it followed by a non-empty string or digits and then this whole thing is
可选, 整个指数是可选的, 这是另一种选择
optional. The whole exponent is optional. S o this is an alternative and more
写这个表达式的简洁的方法, 我, 我总是说服你
compact way to write this expression. To wrap up, I, I always convinced you in this
正则表达式可以描述许多有用的语言的视频, 我们已经看到
video that regular expressions can describe many useful languages. We've seen
一些编程语言的片段但我们也看到了电子邮件地址
some fragments from programming languages but also we saw that e-mail addresses
可以用这种方式指定, 其他的是常规语言的东西
could be specified this way. Other things that are regular languages are things like
电话号码和文件名也是有规律的, 有很多很多的例子
phone numbers and file names are also regular. And there are many, many examples
在日常生活中使用常规语言来描述一些简单的
in everyday life where regular languages are used to describe some simple set of
我还想强调的是, 到目前为止, 我们使用的是常规语言
strings. And I also want to emphasize that so far, we've used regular languages as a
语言规范, 我们用它来定义我们感兴趣的字符串集
language specification. We use it to define the set of strings we're interested
但是, 我们还没有说过如何真正实现词汇
in. But, we haven't said anything about how to actually implement lexical
分析, 我们仍然需要一个实现, 这就是我们以后要讨论的内容
analysis. We still need an implementation. And that's what we'll talk about in future
尤其是视频, 特别是, 我们要研究的是
videos. In particular, in particular, we're going to look at the problem of
给定一个字符串作为一个不规则的表达式, 或者, 我们怎么知道这个字符串是不是
given a string as an irregular expression. Or, how do we know whether that string is
在正则表达式的语言中。
in the language of the regular expression are.